Hey, welcome to our final web exclusive
for my lecture series. So, this again is
your questions asked about the
publishing business and I'm going to be
here for about 30 minutes answering your
questions. Um, and I just want to
preface by saying, hey, thanks for
following along uh this year's recording
of them. We probably won't do this again
for a number of years. So, uh, it was a
wonderful experience and I liked all of
your involvement and I'm glad that I can
get to some web exclusive uh, lecture
content for you. So, here we go. These
are your questions. First one is, how
would you pitch to an agent to represent
you for an inrogress book series with
the first book already indie published?
Um, I would say make some decisions uh,
ahead of time what you're wanting to uh,
an agent for. So, are you wanting to do
what happened with um Fifty Shades of
Gray or some of these where that was an
indie published series that they decided
to make uh traditionally published in
which case generally the author pulls
all the indie published things once a
publication deal is in the works and
rebrands with uh brand new cover art and
things like that and relaunches. uh if
that's what you're wanting to do, uh you
just know that that's kind of what has
happened sometimes with these books in
the past or instead are you getting an
agent because you want the agent to sell
you in foreign markets. Um this is a
thing that agents as I mentioned in the
main lecture do sometimes for indie
published authors is they handle all the
you know overseas rights uh film rights
that sort of stuff. uh what are you
planning to do with that? Knowing
upfront what you're asking for helps you
with your query letter. At that point,
uh, the number I often hear bandied
about, which, um, you know, I don't have
a ton of confirmation on, maybe somebody
in the comments who has done this before
can say whether or not was confirmed,
but I I hear a lot of 10,000 copies
sold, uh, being a pretty good benchmark
for agents, meaning not counting the
free ones that you give away with
various promotions, but actual point of
sale. uh I have sold 10,000 copies um of
this book series putting that in the
query letter and uh I would have a pitch
particular if you can meet them in
person be like I'm an indie author I've
um I've sold x number of copies I think
that uh traditionally publishing some of
these might take me to the next level uh
if you know what are your thoughts and
have the agent chat with you about what
they've done in the past and what
they're looking for or say to them I'm
okay in the US. I know what I'm doing. I
would like to go traditionally published
in other countries. Would you be
interested in handling my foreign
rights? Um, so those are kind of your uh
your your two options there. And uh
there might be people again who have
done something different with this that
can in the comments uh let me know uh
whether or not um they have other
suggestions. In Spain, for example,
having a litter agent is much usually
much less common. Yes.
uh lot of the the foreign markets um
people sell without an agent. In fact,
this uh models what happened in the US
back when science fiction fantasy was
not the powerhouse sales genre. It was
the agents really weren't that
interested. In fact, you really couldn't
support the agents on the income of all
these authors during, you know, the
early days, the the golden age and the
silver age of science fiction. A lot of
the deals were done just with author and
publisher. Um to the point that uh
there's this legacy uh where science
fiction accepted unagented authors for a
much longer time. Like when I was
breaking in, you could still do it
without an agent. U even though agents
have become stagnant because of that
legacy of author publisher
relationships. So uh it tends to be
50/50 or even lower. Uh I'm not
surprised by that. Uh given the chance
generally would you recommend trying to
pitch to publishers alone or get an
agent? Also I've heard that the norm is
an agent here takes from 15 to 20%
sometimes even more. Well um tw even
more would be shocking to me. Um and I
would be uh well not shocking but I
would I would definitely avoid paying
more. 20% is standard for foreign deals
on agents. So basically if I sell in
Spain my agent takes 20%. Why is that?
Because there's a local agent taking 10%
and there's my uh New York agent taking
10%. Um and uh I feel like this is a
fair split considering that selling in
Spain myself uh I could probably do it
now, but early in my career, there's no
way that you can go like the agents all
fly to giant book fairs where they meet
with all the editors and agents from
other countries. It's a very involved
process. Um, so I wouldn't say 20% is
bad if that 20% is what they charge to
sell overseas. Um, but I don't know what
the norm and the standard is uh in given
countries. So I'll just stop there. Um,
given the chance, would you recommend
trying to pitch to publishers alone or
get an agent? I would always recommend
if the option exists to sell to a
publisher directly. Uh, the fewer
middlemen in between you and a sale
generally is just going to be better.
Um, if you have a chance to land an
agent who has a very good track record
at selling new books, um, then it is
worth paying them the percent in order
to do it in general. But the smaller the
market, the less necessary this is.
Spain is actually a pretty decently
sized market uh for a foreign market,
but um really your your places where
fantasy sells best are US, UK, um and
Germany tend to be the top three. Uh and
so I would expect those to be the places
where you're most likely to need an
agent. What would I recommend? Anytime
you can talk directly to an editor, get
an editor excited, uh and sell directly
to them, I would recommend doing that.
if uh the contract negotiations get
complicated um or if the money gets
good, bringing in an agent at that point
might be necessary. I sold without an
agent even in the US. Uh but I got an
agent to once I'd sold it to actually
handle the negotiations. So, and I'm
glad that I did. I'll say that. I'm
currently writing a fantasy novella and
hope for it to be my debut. Well, good
for you. specifically in the realm of
traditional publishing. I
uh novella plus traditional publishing a
little rougher, but we'll talk about it.
I know you touched on how smaller
mid-size presses might uh be a good move
for publishing novellas in your final
video of your lecture series. I did, but
I'm curious about your thoughts on how
novellas fit into the publishing world
overall. Specifically, do you think
trying to break in with a novella would
work? And if so, how should I go about
it? All right. Nollas have an
interesting uh tradition in science
fiction fantasy. Uh, first off, what is
a novella? A novella is defined by the
by the science fiction writing
association as 17,000 words to about 30
to about 50 depending on who you talk
to. I think Cphwa says 17 to 30, but I'm
not 100% sure on that. I know 17 tends
to be about the break point where a
novellet becomes a novella. Uh, but
these are all kind of squishy.
Basically, you're looking at something
that's plotted and paced like a novel,
but just a short novel rather than
plotted and pasteed like a long short
story. That's what a novella is. And
you've probably read some famous books
that technically fit into that range of
novella depending on which numbers
you're using. For instance, uh Christmas
Carol uh is a novella and not a novel.
And um Enders Game started as a novella
uh not a novel. several other like for
instance um Dragonfly by Ann McCaffrey
uh was one I think novella maybe short
maybe it was novellet but won one of the
shorter for fiction categories just as
kind of the opening to the novel before
she wrote the novel. Um, so for the
longest time, a novella or a novellet, a
short novella or a longer novellet would
form the cornerstone for the magazines.
Back in the era where the magazines were
the dominant way that people read
science fiction, fantasy. You would get
a bunch of cool short stories and then
you would have this chunky novella in
the back to really make you feel like
your money was well spent and that you
got a little bit more of a novel
experience. Not all of uh the issues did
this but it was really common to do
that. And that novella was often by an
established author. They would rarely
buy those from non-established author
because that novella like you can
imagine it as a magazine reader. You
like I want to try out new people. I
want to see what people are capable of
but I also want to get my money's worth
and know that there is a very good story
in this that that alone would have been
the uh worth the price of buying the
magazine. So all the short stories in
some ways are a uh are a bonus because I
know I get that cool Azimov novella at
the back of uh this thing and uh for the
longest time that was the market for
novellas. You had real trouble selling
them as a new author. The novella slot
in a uh a magazine was there to be the
name on the cover that drew people to
buy it so that they knew they were
getting that money's worth. Uh sometimes
it's if if it was a really great novella
uh they would buy it and put it in that
slot even by a new author. Uh but that's
kind of the history of the novella.
That's why an McAffrey had this
dragonfly that was that was such a big
deal before the novel was even written.
I think they called the novella
versionwatch
uh and things like that. Over time the
magazines kind of died off. There are
still some good ones. Clark's World and
whatnot. They're mostly digital first um
right now or they focus on the digital
though they do have there are some print
components. Um at that point for a while
novellas became a great way to break in
on ebook nollas. I wrote uh Emperor's
Soul right during this era uh kind of at
the forefront of this before it really
took off uh back when you know you
didn't really know how to sell a novela
but you we started putting them up on
Kindle for a couple of bucks and for a
while that did really well. Uh this was
back in kind of the gold rush era of uh
Kindle where people were looking for
things that were kind of inexpensive to
try out their Kindle on and whatnot. And
uh during that gold rush era um Hugh
Howey and some other people hit on a
cool idea where you could release a uh
book as a series of novellas. This is
how wool which became the the television
show silo that you might be familiar
with uh is just like a group of novellas
that together became a novel. Um all of
this led to um tour.com as an imprint
starting up which was publishing kind of
literary uh high-end if you would say
nollas uh with the editorial team
focused on it. And a lot of the best
novella winners uh over the last years
in the various categories came from
places like tour.com that were hunting
for kind of literary uh stylized um
often uh they were looking for diverse
voices uh for these imprints to have
these um you might call them award-b uh
sort of things using that not as a
pjorative. uh a lot of the great films
and stories we have would be have
considered but they're looking for an
eye for uh kind of literary excellence
for these sorts of things. Uh and that
is been lately the dominant way that uh
novellas have fit into the publishing
world. Very long answer to your simple
question, but how should you go about
it? Well, if uh if yours is a story that
can fit tour.com, uh that is often the
best place. But again, they do focus on
diverse voices and uh literary styling.
Uh for that, um novellas are still an
excellent way to break yourself in um
indie published. Uh they can be a way
that people can buy something for fairly
inexpensive to try you out on. The gold
rush era of indie publishing is gone,
however, and a novella just kind of
sitting there by itself without the
support of a full indie published career
is probably just not going to sell um
that well. That's what my gut says in
today's market. Unless you are going
full in. If traditional publishing is
your way, then you are looking at
tour.com or you are looking for going to
one of these smaller midsize presses and
trying to publish more of a prestige
piece uh novella that they can hope will
get some award um recognition to drive
your name or you are looking at the few
remaining magazines being willing to
stick you in that um that spot. The
large traditional publishers are not
looking for novellas. It is not worth
the money to get those on the shelves in
bookstores because people in bookstores
don't traditionally buy nollas very
much. They are they made the effort to
get to a bookstore. They're generally
looking for something bigger than that.
Not to say it can't happen, particularly
for a longer novella. Um, a lot of
novellas that sell right now are written
by authors writing stories that don't
quite fit in their regular novels, such
as what I've done with some Stormlight
Archive novelas, and those have sold
very well, but they're already selling
on my name. you'd have a lot more
trouble doing that without a book uh to
support it. So, there's a whole bunch of
context. I hope you can piece together
from that a strategy for yourself. I
wrote the first draft of a book that I
fear ended up being too close to a mega
bestseller and plot structure, but not
in terms of my protagonist. In
publishing, is it a really bad idea to
try to pitch a debut novel that comes
close to a super bestseller? No, this is
generally not a bad idea. Um, it depends
on how close though. If you had the
exact same idea as Hunger Games and
everyone who reads the pitch is going to
be like, "Oh, it's just Hunger Games
again." You might have trouble. However,
my instinct says, generally authors are
more aware of this than readers or
publishers are, and authors are more
sensitive to this than readers or
publisher are. My guess is that it's
probably fine, not having read the book.
um that the plot structure being similar
as long as your protagonist and your
setting uh feel distinctive, you really
shouldn't worry as much as you probably
are. Um does this mean my idea is not
fresh? Well, no idea is super fresh.
Everything's been done before. Your take
on is important. That said, some ideas
do feel well worn. This is the the
problem with me giving advice without
knowing what the idea is. Once in a
while you'll have something and it goes
out and everyone's like, "This just
feels like we've done this too much."
Um, and that could be a problem. It's
not like I think it's likely to be, but
it could be. Uh, did you shoot yourself
in the foot? No. Um, I think you should
try to query your book. Um, or you
should, if you're trying to indie
publish, either way, I would give the
book to some some readers and see if you
can get some readers. see if you can
trade some readers on some uh places and
see if without you telling them, they
pick up and be like, "Wow, this reads
exactly like X uh and see if they're
bothered by it. If they even write back
and be like, you know what, I love this.
It reminded me of X. You're in good
shape." Uh that's not a problem. So, um
I would not do a major rewrite. I would
stick to your guns and tell the story
that you wanted to tell
and make sure that you've got your
distinctive voice in your protagonist
and uh and you know some of the details
in the setting and things like that. Uh
and see what people say. See if you're
getting the uh it feels too much like X.
Um again, my guess is not. So go
forward. I think you're fine. At what
point should you try to find an agent?
Does your book need to be ready to be
published already through alpha and beta
readers? Along with that, how do you
find alpha and beta readers and what
distinguishes the two groups? Uh,
excellent questions here. So, what point
should you try to find an agent? Um, it
doesn't have to be publication ready,
but if you're planning to use alpha and
beta readers, I would have gone through
that already before I sent it out
personally. Um, I am a big believer in
them. There I should point out there are
some authors, I did say this in the
lectures that do not like doing this at
all. So your process may not work with
alpha and beta readers. Uh but how do
you find them? Generally uh I found my
the majority of my early beta readers by
working on a science fiction magazine um
at the local college. if you happen to
be at college uh and if you know or or
whatnot and there is a local magazine on
campus a lot of them have them going and
volunteering and be becoming part of
that and learning like actually doing
the work reading slush for them and
seeing what new writers are submitting
right now to slush that's getting
rejected and be like hm what can I learn
from that what's getting bought what can
I learn from that um you know when I say
bought for these student magazines
usually it's a it's you know a $25 gift
certificate But uh it is getting you
know passing through and people are
reading it and liking it. What's working
and get to know that group? Um find um
that sort of thing. Find the con crowd
who um who puts on science fiction
conventions and see if you can volunteer
for the writing track. Now, one thing I
should warn you about is longestablished
writing groups and things like that tend
to have um oified in a way and may not
be as good for a new reader just kind or
author entering in to that group. uh
they have their own ways of doing things
and um you know there is this this sort
of long-standing writing groups that
have become support groups for people
who are solidly um in the amateur space
and after many years have kind of
settled into that role where they know
they're doing this uh for amateur work.
If your goal is to straight up publish
and make a living at it, um some of
those sorts of groups might not be good
for you. Uh I would recommend that uh
you start mingling online um with people
who are you know themselves writers and
it is a hard process to find early
readers that are good uh because too
many early readers don't know that their
job is just to read the book and give
their gut impression. They instead want
to change your book or try to fix your
book. And that is not what a beta reader
should be doing. Beta readers should
just be giving their honest opinion on
how they felt reading the book. And you
should never be listening to any one
beta reader too much. Uh what's the
difference between an alpha and a beta?
Alpha for me are people who are industry
insiders. Um when I say alpha reads, I
am giving it to people who have a long
relationship with me. Um and they know
what they're doing in the publishing
industry and I let them say you should
do this. You should change this. Um beta
readers I don't want to hear that from.
Beta readers are a test audience.
They're just people that are the market
that would like my book and how did they
feel? Uh where were they bored? Uh where
were they excited? That sort of stuff.
Um as a new writer, it's going to be
hard for you to get a large group of
those because you are competing for
their attention with published books.
So, usually you're going to have some
hybrid between what I just described and
you're going to find other authors who
you're going to be trading books with
and you're going to be giving feedback
on theirs and they're going to be giving
feedback on yours even if it's not in a
writing group situation. Uh it is one of
those things that's hard. You can start
with your family and friends as well.
Just know that it's hard for them to be
objective. Uh so, uh don't let your beta
readers ruin your book. Don't listen to
any one of them too much. Uh, but you do
want to try to get an a feel for what
people how people respond to your work
and what you think of those responses
and how to interpret it. Uh, remember
that beta readers are generally bad at
picking out what is wrong, but they are
good at picking out that something is
wrong. Usually, they'll have the wrong
reason why they don't like something.
Um, and that's where that that problem
comes in, right? You can probably see
how that would go. If they are right in
noticing that the book is slow for them,
but they're wrong in saying you should
put it in an action scene because well,
you the reason it's actually slow is
you've made the wrong promises or this
feels like a tangent. You might go
through and fix it as the way that they
suggest but then just make more problems
and not fix the one that's there. Uh so
at what point should you try to find an
agent? I talked a lot about uh those but
not answer that question. I would say oh
I did answer it. uh once you are
comfortable that another draft on this
book would be taking a lot of sideways
steps instead of steps forward. Uh for
most authors, I would say we're not
talking by like 12th draft. We're
talking talking like third or fourth
draft. Uh is where it's probably time to
start looking at an agent if that's
something you want to do. Regarding bios
on pitches and query letters, how
relevant is academic publishing? Not at
all. Unless you're writing uh a book
that is very related to your academic
publishing. I'm an academic researcher
with plans to publish articles and maybe
a manuscript of my thesis before
publishing fantasy. Uh again, if you are
a medievalist writing about a specific
time period and you have uh genuine
expertise uh like if I were a professor
of uh of Anglo-Saxon history and say and
I have written uh what I consider a very
good Anglo-Saxon inspired fantasy, I
would mention it just like that. I'm not
sure if I should mention or show that
I've been uh gone through the
peer-reviewed editorial pro editing
process, for example. Nope, they don't
care. They really don't. Um they
uh that's probably given you some good
experience, but unless for instance,
let's say that you are uh you've done
all of this research on quantum
mechanics and you're writing a novel
that involves that, then I would um I I
would include it. Let's say that what
you do is you are a an academic uh
researcher for like, you know,
pharmaceuticals and whether these sorts
of drugs work in this situation, but
you're writing an epic fantasy. They're
not going to care. And I I might put it
in my bio about who you are, but I
definitely wouldn't put it in such a way
that they're supposed to think that this
is relevant. How um would negotiations
work for special editions of your book
through a company like Folio Society or
Broken Binding? Would those be
negotiated into your contract? Would
those be negotiated later? uh if the
books uh sell well enough, I recommend
keeping those rights um with New York
publishers. Uh that is, as I'm told,
much harder to do than it used to be uh
because of uh me, and I apologize for
that. Uh me doing giant special
editions. Um I'm like the George the way
that George Lucas, like if you've heard
the story about Star Wars, they didn't
really do merchandise for movies back in
the day. George Lucas kept his
merchandising rights and then they made
billions. No one ever let a a a a
filmmaker keep their merchandising
rights after that happened. Um back in
the early 2000s, uh special editions
just, you know, even with some places
like uh Subterrain Press and Folio
Society, they just didn't they weren't
such huge money that the publishers even
cared about them. Generally, the money
coming in was small enough that
negotiating the contracts was a bigger
hassle and cost more in lawyer time than
the money that would come in. And so,
when I said, "I'm going to start keeping
these," my publishers were just like,
"Yeah, sure, fine." Uh, and then I went
on to make a very large amount of money
off of them. Um, and a lot of companies
um started up that were doing this. Um,
again, I can't take a portfolio society.
They've been doing this for a long time
and doing excellent work. Uh but uh
definitely some of the more popularized
ones that are doing uh um special
editions started up in part because of
what I did. Um this makes it much harder
to keep your your rights. Uh I would
recommend that you do it or at least put
into the contract what it looks like.
generally um these for for someone like
Folio Society uh they only do kind of
the best of the best and therefore
um if you are lucky enough to have Solio
Society want to make one of yours uh
then you're in a good spot but of course
they sell a lot of their editions for
like $700 uh for that reason I would try
to keep them if you fail I would try to
have good language and your agent and or
uh attorney will know how to put that
language in. How does the publishing
industry feel about authors who are
self-published and making a good living
at it when they try uh start trying to
move to more traditional publishing? Uh
these days um the attitude is very
positive uh toward indie authors. Uh in
my experience talking to indie authors
your mileage may vary. You may still run
into I think most of these are gone but
for a long time the publishing industry
was like oh you're self-published
whatever. uh and they've moved away from
that and seeing indie publishing as kind
of a way to find the best and try to uh
coax them into traditional publishing.
So how do they feel? They see these days
as indie publishing is one of these sort
of uh they would consider it a proof of
concept, a place where um ideas are
proven and stories are proven and a
place for them to look for things that
they can uh that they can buy. um that
puts you in a pretty good position
because you don't have to say yes. Uh if
you are self-publishing, making a good
living at it, um then you can be very
very picky and I would talk with some
authors who have made that jump and see
what they think about it and whether
they are glad that it happened or not.
Uh so um yeah, I I would point you
toward them, but generally the attitude
is positive. I mean, Fifty Shades of
Gray uh was so successful that Random
House gave a $5,000 check to every
employee in the entire company. We are
talking about thousands and thousands of
people. If I live in a foreign country,
how hard is it to publish in the US and
other English-speaking countries? Um it
is hard. Uh not impossible, but it is
hard. The main trick you're going to run
into is uh getting your story into
English because the US sits in this kind
of uh privileged position in the
publishing industry where the US has
enough and strong enough of a market
that it doesn't need to look toward uh
foreign published things in order to
sell to its audience. Um because of that
only the things that sell the very best
in foreign countries do US publishers
buy and take on the cost of translation.
If you are writing in English then the
difficulty is uh not much higher than it
is for everyone else. If you are already
writing in English uh your difficulty is
people who live here have a better
chance of being able to meet editors and
agents by going to conventions. Uh it's
just cheaper for them to do. Uh, and
that is still a way that a lot of people
get published. Um, but um, editors
aren't caring where you're from. They're
caring how good the story is. Uh, and
they will not um, in my experience look
with any prejudice on a book from a um,
foreign country as long as the book is
good. Um sometimes you know uh having an
advocate uh locally if you have some
author friends who are published and you
are published in your country um they
can facilitate like three body problem
coming to the US was helped by um by Ted
Chang um quite a bit uh and things like
that. So,
um, so yeah, that sort of thing. Um, but
if you're writing in a foreign language,
uh, you'll have to get it into English
most likely and take that expense upon
yourself before you can sub submit it in
the US or you're going to have to sell
really well in your local language
enough that you know the people who have
made it over here are like Sepkovski
level sales or threebody problem um, or
you know, Cornel Cornelia Funka from
Germany. um some of these authors uh
have have made it uh in translation. Um
it just it's a little stacked against
you because the US publishers don't have
to pay for books in translation and the
publishers in other countries generally
will pay for that translation for an
English book going to their language
because they have the proof of concept
in the US market of something selling
really well. There you are. Uh thank you
for your questions. Uh those were
excellent questions and once again thank
you so much for hanging out. uh being in
the comment section. I actually get your
comments still to my phone. I don't
respond that often, but uh but the all
the comments on YouTube videos come to
my phone. They tend to come in a flood
and I only see like one out of a
hundred. Uh but I do glance at my phone
now and then and see what you guys have
written uh in the comment section. So uh
so thank you for that. Thank you for
what you have to say. Thank you for your
participation. Uh keep writing. I know
it's it's a hard world out there for for
publishing and I I give you my best and
hopefully this has been a good resource
to you. Uh if you have uh helpful
feedback or other answers to these
questions uh leave in the comments
particularly if you we had a couple of
questions from people uh writing
overseas um trying to maybe break into
the English market or things like that.
If you have experience there please
share your experience. Uh I would love
to hear what is h what you think uh
people who have done it. Uh same thing
with uh the indie authors. If you've
been thinking of going traditional or if
you have gone traditional and either
have gone back to indie or if you have
experience in that realm and you are
watching these please post your
thoughts. Uh what your experience trumps
my theory. Uh so I would like to hear
what your experience is. We'll be back
in probably five years. Uh maybe maybe
more. uh to do another round of
recordings of my lectures. So these are
the ones that will stand as our newest
lectures for the next 5 years. uh and I
hope that uh they will be a
long-standing resource for everyone in
the industry.